Status:	New	Priority:	Should have
Author:	Jacob Floyd	Category:	
Created:	2013-08-29	Assigned To:	
Updated:	2013-08-29	Due date:	

Sprint:

PHP Version:

Has patch: No

Complexity:

Subject: Improve speed of Files::readDirectoryRecursively using RecursiveDirectoryIterator?

Description

Basics (TL;DR)

TYPO3/Flow/Utility/Files::readDirectoryRecursively uses \DirectoryIterator instead of \RecursiveDirectoryIterator. I suspect that an implementation using \RecursiveDirectoryIterator would be faster.

Let's write a version of readDirectoryRecursively that uses \RecursiveDirectoryIterator and profile the two versions to see which one is faster.

Background

When I asked about it in IRC, ChristianM said this:

ChristianM: if I remember right there was some oddness to the RecursiveDirectoryIterator that we wanted to avoid but I don't remember the specifics

Consider this a selection of PHP Release dates

```
01 May 2008 - PHP 5.2.6
10 May 2008 - Flow's Files::readDirectoryRecursively introduced
30 Jun 2009 - PHP 5.3.0
17 Sep 2009 - PHP 5.2.11
19 Nov 2009 - PHP 5.3.1
```

According to the Changelog for \RecursiveDirectoryIterator

- 5.2.11 Introduced RecursiveDirectoryIterator::FOLLOW_SYMLINKS
- 5.3.0 Extends FilesystemIterator (which extends DirectoryIterator) instead of DirectoryIterator
- 5.3.0 Implements SeekableIterator
- 5.3.1 Introduced RecursiveDirectoryIterator::FOLLOW_SYMLINKS

We don't even support 5.2 anymore, and haven't for a long time. I suspect that the oddness with \RecursiveDirectoryIterator has been fixed already, so I think that using \RecursiveDirectoryIterator is probably feasible now.

Stub Method

This is the same function only it doesn't filter hidden directories, just hidden files.

```
static public function readDirectoryRecursively($path, $suffix = NULL, $returnRealPath = FALSE, $returnDotFiles = FALSE,
&$filenames = array()) {
    if (!is_dir($path)) {
        throw new Exception("" . $path . "" is no directory.', 1207253462);
    }
```

2015-08-04 1/3

History

#1 - 2013-08-29 17:55 - Jacob Floyd

OK. This one is functionally equivalent including removing hidden directories. However, it uses \RecursiveCallbackFilterIterator which is only available in PHP 5.4.

```
static public function readDirectoryRecursively($path, $suffix = NULL, $returnRealPath = FALSE, $returnDotFiles = FALSE) {
  if (!is_dir($path)) {
     throw new Exception("". $path. " is no directory.', 1207253462);
  $suffixLength = strlen($suffix);
  $filter = function ($fileInfo, $pathname, $iterator) use ($suffix, $suffixLength, $returnDotFiles) {
     $filename = $fileInfo->getFilename();
    if ($returnDotFiles === FALSE && $filename[0] === '.') {
       return FALSE;
    }
     if (($fileInfo->isFile() && ($suffix === NULL || substr($filename, -$suffixLength) === $suffix)) || $iterator->hasChildren()) {
       return TRUE;
    }
     return FALSE;
  };
  $directoryIterator = new \RecursiveIteratorIterator(
     new \RecursiveCallbackFilterIterator(
       new \RecursiveDirectoryIterator(
          $path,
          //defaults: \FilesystemIterator::KEY AS PATHNAME|\FilesystemIterator::CURRENT AS FILEINFO
          \FilesystemIterator::UNIX_PATHS|\FilesystemIterator::SKIP_DOTS|\FilesystemIterator::FOLLOW_SYMLINKS
       ), $filter
    )
  );
```

2015-08-04 2/3

```
foreach ($directoryIterator as $pathname => $fileInfo) {
    $filenames[] = self::getUnixStylePath(($returnRealPath === TRUE ? realpath($pathname) : $pathname));
}
return $filenames;
}
```

#2 - 2013-08-29 19:49 - Jacob Floyd

I've been working on this, because I needed a more robust filtering mechanism when using readDirectoriesRecursively.

You can see my final version, based on the one in the previous comment here

2015-08-04 3/3